{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One of these structures named for Alexander the Great is known for its red color and found near Gorgon. After the Battle of the Allia, one of these structures was built and named for Servius Tullius; that structure was surpassed by the Aurelian line, built in the 3rd century AD. For ten points, name this type of defensive structure that was built by the Qin Dynasty to guard the northern border of China.",
      "answer": [
        "walls",
        "Great Wall of Gorgon",
        "Servian Walls",
        "Aurelian Walls",
        "Great Wall of China"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After dropping out of Reed College, this man audited a calligraphy class that inspired the “multiple typefaces” of one of his products. A Walter Isaacson biography of this man inspired a 2015 film in which Seth Rogen plays a colleague of this man, Steve Wozniak. After this man was kicked off the Lisa project, he led the Macintosh project until resigning from the company he co-founded in 1976. For ten points, name this business icon and longtime CEO of Apple.",
      "answer": "Steve Jobs"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1976, George H.W. Bush took over a leadership role in this organization for slightly less than a year. The Family Jewels were a set of papers about this organization. This agency trained a group of exiles called Brigade 2506, which was decisively defeated after an amphibious landing at the Bay of Pigs. For ten points, name this American organization, based in Langley, Virginia, that manages international espionage.",
      "answer": "Central Intelligence Agency or CIA"
    },
    {
      "question": "A palace partially named for this color was the residence of British monarchs for most of the 16th and 17th centuries. William Adelin died in a disaster named after a ship of this color. The Ditchley Portrait shows Queen Elizabeth wearing an outfit of this color. A rose of this color was used to symbolize the House of York, as opposed to the red rose used by the House of Lancaster. For ten points, name this color of the chalk-laden Cliffs of Dover.",
      "answer": [
        "white",
        "Whitehall Palace, White Ship Disaster, white rose, White Cliffs of Dover"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This location included a radar station at Opana Point, which was staffed by Joseph Lockard and George Elliot. This facility includes Ford Island, Hickam Field, and Wheeler Field, where grounded aircraft were destroyed by Val bombers. This facility’s Battleship Row was home to the Pacific Fleet’s Oklahoma and Arizona. For ten points, name this American naval base on Oahu that was attacked on December 7th, 1941.",
      "answer": [
        "Naval Station Pearl Harbor",
        "descriptive answers, such as “the naval base at Pearl Harbor”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s Special Field Order Number 15 provided for the confiscation of land along the Atlantic coast to be allotted among freed slaves, which became the basis for the saying “Forty Acres and a Mule.” This commander presented 25,000 bales of cotton to Abraham Lincoln as a Christmas gift when he captured Savannah in December 1864, the culmination of a campaign of total war. For ten points, name this Union general who captured Atlanta to begin his “March to the Sea.”",
      "answer": "William Tecumseh Sherman"
    },
    {
      "question": "Two of these figures, Mushka and Pchyolka, were purposely killed in 1960 to prevent foreign powers from inspecting their vehicle. Strelka, another of these figures, gave birth to a child named Pushinka who was given as a gift to John F. Kennedy in 1961. The most famous of these animals was locked in a box for weeks of training and died of overheating after a separation failure, having completed four orbits aboard Sputnik 2. Laika was one of, for ten points, what trained animal cosmonauts?",
      "answer": [
        "Soviet space dogs",
        "descriptive answers of “the dogs that the USSR launched into space",
        "promptonpartialanswers,suchas“dog”or“Soviets”or“Russians”or“cosmonaut”or“astronaut”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Laryngeal examples of these constructs are generally not found within the English language. The dropping of the voiceless glottal fricative type of these constructs took place during the 13th century. The place and manner of articulation are typically both given when categorizing these constructs, which differ from a similar construct in that they require a complete or partial closure of the vocal tract. For ten points, name these linguistic constructs that are often contrasted with vowels.",
      "answer": "consonants"
    },
    {
      "question": "A group of people protesting Dick Wilson’s corruption occupied this site under the direction of Russell Means in 1973. Stephen Vincent Benet’s poem “American Names” references this location, noting “I shall not be there. I shall rise and pass. Bury my heart at” this location. This site in the Pine Ridge Indian Reservation was the location of a violent episode when Black Coyote refused to surrender his rifle to U.S. troops. For ten points, name this site of an 1890 massacre of Lakota Sioux.",
      "answer": [
        "Wounded Knee",
        "Bury My Heart at Wounded Knee",
        "Wounded Knee Massacre"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This cause was supported by Horace Greeley’s pamphlet “Prayer of Twenty Millions,” which urged enforcement of the Confiscation Acts. People who proposed secession and opposed this cause were called Fire-Eaters. William Lloyd Garrison burned a copy of the Constitution because it failed to support this cause, which he advocated for in The Liberator. For ten points, name this cause that was achieved via the 13th Amendment and the Emancipation Proclamation.",
      "answer": [
        "abolition of slavery",
        "word forms",
        "any answers related to freeing slaves"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Charles Lennox Richardson died after a holder of this position gave the order to “expel the barbarians.” The Jewel Voice Broadcast was delivered by the holder of this position. Between the 9th and 12th centuries, holders of this position frequently married women of the Fujiwara clan. In 1946, the holder of this position renounced his divine descent from the sun goddess Amaterasu. For ten points, name this position held by Hirohito during World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Emperor of Japan",
          "word forms"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Before the Imperial Palace was moved to Edo, the imperial capital was this city on Honshu, northeast of Osaka.",
        "answer": "Kyoto"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Natives who worked near this location were put on the silver roll as opposed to the gold roll, which was reserved for Americans and Europeans. John McCain was born in a U.S. administrative zone named for this location. The Torrijos-Carter Treaties specified a twenty year time frame for this location to pass from American control to that of a Central American country. For ten points, name this waterway, opened in 1914, that connects the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans.",
        "answer": [
          "Panama Canal",
          "Panama Canal Zone"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "American interest in the Panama Canal began when this president acquired rights to the area via the Hay-Bunau-Varilla Treaty.",
        "answer": "Theodore “Teddy” Roosevelt"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the aftermath of this event, Governor Kathleen Blanco emphasized that National Guardsmen were armed with M-16s and would “shoot and kill.” Two unarmed civilians were killed by police at Danziger Bridge after this disaster. Michael Brown was told he was “doing a heck of a job” dealing with the devastation wrought by this event before he was fired from his post as Director of FEMA by George W. Bush. For ten points, name this 2005 natural disaster, a hurricane that devastated New Orleans and the Gulf Coast.",
        "answer": "Hurricane Katrina"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Army Corps of Engineers determined that most of the lives lost in New Orleans during Katrina were the result of the failure of these earthen protections, 53 of which were breeched by the storm surge.",
        "answer": [
          "levees",
          "dikes",
          "floodbanks"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man advocated for a “Common European Home” to prevent the threat of war from rival factions. This man, who removed Andrei Gromyko as foreign minister, began a policy of nonintervention known as the Sinatra Doctrine. The Gang of Eight targeted this man in a coup that was thwarted by a speech given atop a tank by Boris Yeltsin. The reforming policy of glasnost was championed by, for ten points, what final leader of the Soviet Union?",
        "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned Sinatra Doctrine applied to the USSR’s allies within this defensive pact, a rival to NATO during the Cold War. ANSWER:Warsaw Pact(accepttheTreaty of Friendship, Cooperation, and Mutual Assistance) (5) Jedidiah Huntington led efforts to circumvent this law, which was succeeded by Macon’s Bill No. 2 shortly after its repeal. In a famous cartoon criticizing its effects, a man carrying a barrel labeled “super fine” attempts to break free of a snapping turtle’s grasp. The “Ograbme” cartoon attacked, for ten points, what 1807 legislation enacted by Thomas Jefferson that was intended to block trade with Great Britain and France?",
        "answer": [
          "Embargo Act of 1807 BONUS: The Embargo Act was a response to this British practice of forcing sailors to serve in its navy, done in 1807 to four Americans onboard the USS Chesapeake who the British claimed were defectors from their navy. ANSWER: impressment",
          "additional information, such as the press",
          "the press gang"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Excavations at El-Haraneya showed that the most famous of these structures was linked by causeway to the Valley Temple. An early example of these structures consisted of six mastabas stacked upon each other; that building was built by Djoser and designed by the architect Imhotep. Examples of these structures commissioned by Menkaure, Khafre, and Khufu are found near the Sphinx. For ten points, identify these ancient Egyptian tombs.",
        "answer": "Egyptian pyramids"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Great Pyramids and the Sphinx are found on the outskirts of modern Cairo in this city.",
        "answer": "Giza"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After Reinhard Scheer led this force at an indecisive battle near the Skagerrak, Scheer recommended that this force loosen its restrictions on attacking without warning. This military force was dismantled at Scapa Flow on Ludwig von Reuter’s orders, hoping that it would not be divided up between the victors after the Armistice. Alfred von Tirpitz revolutionized, for ten points, what military force that included the High Seas Fleet and which brought the US into World War I by sinking the Lusitania?",
        "answer": [
          "Imperial German Navy",
          "High Seas Fleet before mentioned",
          "mentions of German submarines after “restrictions” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Alfred von Tirpitz assisted this Kaiser of Germany in the expansion of the Imperial German Navy. This man abdicated the throne after Germany lost World War I.",
        "answer": "Kaiser Wilhelm II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This history of this disease was examined by Randy Shilts in his book And The Band Played On. Teenager Ryan White’s expulsion from school after contracting this disease inspired a 1990 law providing healthcare funding to people living with this disease. Critics of the Reagan administration have blamed homophobic policy makers for ignoring the crisis of, for ten points, what disease that is caused by the HIV virus?",
        "answer": "Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome or HIV/AIDS"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ryan White was from this state, which suffered its largest AIDS outbreak in 2015. Mike Pence, while serving as this state’s governor, reluctantly backed some needle exchange programs in an attempt to stop the outbreak.",
        "answer": "Indiana"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Curse of Tippecanoe...",
      "prompt": "Name the the curse of tippecanoe......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Supposedly meant death for the holders of what elected political office, including Abe Lincoln?",
          "answer": "US President"
        },
        {
          "question": "First struck what man, who fought at Tippecanoe and died after just 31 days in office?",
          "answer": "William Henry Harrison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Struck at intervals of how many years between elections?",
          "answer": "20 years"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was “broken” when what man didn’t die after being shot by John Hinckley in 1981?",
          "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Struck what man in Buffalo, New York?",
          "answer": "William McKinley"
        },
        {
          "question": "Struck what man via unknown causes in 1923?",
          "answer": "William Harding"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is alternately named for what leader of the Shawnee who was killed two years after the Battle of Tippecanoe?",
          "answer": "Tecumseh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was supposedly set by what man, the brother of that Shawnee leader?",
          "answer": [
            "Tenskwatawa",
            "the Prophet"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "17th Century England",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Virgin Queen” of England who died in 1603, ending the House of Tudor.",
          "answer": "Elizabeth I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of disaster that destroyed St. Paul’s Cathedral and thousands of houses in London in 1666.",
          "answer": "Great Fire of London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Architect who re-designed St. Paul’s and dozens of other churches after that disaster.",
          "answer": "Sir Christopher Wren"
        },
        {
          "question": "Street where that disaster began in a bakery.",
          "answer": "Pudding Lane"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who recorded his account of that disaster, and an earlier plague, in a famous diary.",
          "answer": "Samuel Pepys , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious group that, according to Titus Oates, supposedly planned the Popish Plot to assassinate the king in 1678.",
          "answer": [
            "Roman Catholics",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King of England overthrown by William and Mary in the 1688 Glorious Revolution.",
          "answer": [
            "James II of England",
            "James VII of Scotland, but do not"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Acts that required public employees to be members of the Church of England, opposed by that king.",
          "answer": "Test Acts"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ottoman Empire",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country with capital Ankara that was borne out of the fallen empire.",
          "answer": "Turkey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secular founder of that country who fought in World War I.",
          "answer": [
            "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
            "either",
            "both names"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle where that founder defended the Dardanelles against a British amphibious attack, a major Ottoman victory.",
          "answer": "Battle of Gallipoli"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that gained its independence from the Ottomans in 1832 after fighting in Athens.",
          "answer": "Greece"
        },
        {
          "question": "Elite Ottoman infantrymen who were kidnapped as young boys and forcibly converted to Islam.",
          "answer": "janissary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ethnic group subjected to a genocide by the Ottomans during World War I.",
          "answer": "Armenians"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian tsar who fought the Pruth River Campaign against the Ottomans.",
          "answer": [
            "Peter the Great",
            "Peter I"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event prompted a message from John XXIII [23], in which he begged “all governments not to remain deaf to this cry of humanity.” During this event, negotiations were mediated by U Thant, and Adlai Stevenson famously agitated for an (20 pts)",
        "answer from Valerian Zorin. This event was ended with the removal of (10 pts)",
        "Jupiter weapon systems from Turkey, and it led to the creation of the Moscow-Washington hotline. For ten points, name this 1962 crisis in which the Soviet Union attempted to place weapons on a Caribbean island."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Cuban Missile Crisis",
        "October Crisis",
        "descriptive answers of a diplomatic crisis regarding ballistic missiles placed in Cuba"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this election year, Harold Stassen was told “you can’t shoot an idea with a gun” after supporting a mandatory communist registry in this election year. Strom Thurmond ran on the breakaway (20 pts)",
        "Dixiecrat ticket in this election year. In a famous photograph taken in this year, a man holds up an early edition of the (10 pts)",
        "Chicago Daily Tribune announcing the wrong outcome of the presidential election. For ten points, name this election year in which Thomas Dewey actually lost to Harry Truman, who thus earned a full second term in office."
      ],
      "answer": "U.S. Presidential Election of 1948"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a legend from this country, a woman who tries to ride her newlywed husband’s horse is thrown off and bounces on her skirt all the way to the moon. Slue-Foot (20 pts)",
        "Sue rode a catfish down a river in this country, and a man in this country dies after beating a steam powered hammer in a steel-driving contest. (10 pts)",
        "Pecos Bill and John Henry are two characters from the folklore of, for ten points, what country where Paul Bunyan’s birth supposedly occurred in Wisconsin or Minnesota?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "United States of America",
        "USA",
        "America"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This general defeated the Marathas at the Battle of Assaye in his first major victory. This commander ordered the building of Portugal’s Lines of Torres Vedras, a defense against Andr´e Mass´ena approved by (20 pts)",
        "Lord Castlereagh; two years later, this man routed Auguste Marmont at Salamanca, a key battle of the Peninsular War. In 1815, this commander’s forces were joined by (10 pts)",
        "Gebhard von Blucher’s Prussian troops near Brussels in his most crucial victory. For ten points, name this British general who defeated Napoleon at the Battle of Waterloo."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington",
        "either",
        "both underlined portions"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A polychoral style of music was developed in this city by Giovanni Gabrielli. This city was the final home of a composer who depicted the mistress of Nero in The Coronation of Poppea. Claudio Monteverdi worked in this city, where the (20 pts)",
        "Ospedale della Piet`a employed the “Red Priest” who composed The Four Seasons. (10 pts)",
        "Antonio Vivaldi lived in, for ten points, what Italian city where opera was staged during Carnival and the barcarole was sung by gondoliers rowing along its canals?"
      ],
      "answer": "Venice"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) James Habersham promoted slavery in this colony, whose original charter banned slavery and liquor. The southern border of this colony expanded to the Saint (20 pts)",
        "Marys River after the English victory in the French and Indian War. For its first twenty years, this colony was governed by a Board of Trustees, who had initially intended it as a home for English (10 pts)",
        "debtors. James Oglethorpe founded, for ten points, what US colony that served as a southern buffer between the English colonies and Spanish Florida?"
      ],
      "answer": "Georgia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This region’s Catholic nobles formed the Union of Green Mountain to contest George Podebrad’s claim to this region’s kingdom, which he contested with Hungarian King Matthias Corvinus. The House of Luxembourg ruled this kingdom under the (20 pts)",
        "Blind King John, who died at the Battle of Crecy. In 1618, two Catholic regents were (10 pts)",
        "defenestrated in a city in this kingdom, helping trigger the Thirty Years’ War. For ten points, name this region in the modern-day Czech Republic which, because French people in the 19th century believed the Romani came from this region, names an unattached artistic lifestyle."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of Bohemia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A work dedicated to this man features friezes on which Ernest Bairstow carved the names of states. On the day that this man said “Let us have faith that right makes might” in the (20 pts)",
        "Cooper Union speech, he was photographed at Mathew Brady’s studio in New York. The Piccirilli brothers carved a sculpture of this man that had been designed by (10 pts)",
        "Daniel Chester French; that sculpture is the focus of a memorial at the west end of a reflecting pool on the National Mall. For ten points, name this American president whose memorial building in Washington, DC features inscriptions of the Gettysburg Address."
      ],
      "answer": "Abraham Lincoln"
    }
  ]
}